# Jag Batth

Healthcare Analyst with a background in Medicine and Technology. Experience with patient relationship, care and treatment implementation with the knowledge and power of data analytics for a multi-perspective approach to healthcare solutions.

in <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jag-batth/">https://www.linkedin.com/in/jag-batth/</a>

https://github.com/jagpreetbatth

https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/jagpreet.batth#!/

Houston, Texas(832) 612-9682

jagpreetbatth@gmail.com

# Education

# Data Analytics & Visualizations

April 2021 - Feb 2021

# **Surgery Internship**

June 2009 - June 2010

#### **Doctor of Medicine**

May 2004 - Nov 2008

# Bachelor of Science Dean's List

Sep 2001 – June 2003

# Career Foundry Data Analytics Program – Certified Data Analyst

Specialization: Healthcare Data Analysis

A 10-month, 500+ hours intensive course for data analysts focusing on advanced analytical concepts, fundamentals, methodology, and industry-standard approach to data analysis tools and functions.

# **Stony Brook University Hospital Center**

Emphasis: Surgical Technique and Application

# **Ross University School of Medicine**

Emphasis: Surgery/Anatomy

# **University of California - Los Angeles (UCLA)**

Major: Biochemistry/Biology Minor: Computer Technology

# **Professional Experience**

# Healthcare Development Manager

July 2020 – Nov 2021

# Sugar Land Methodist Hospital - Orthopedic Surgery Group -Sugar Land, TX

- Identified business demand requirements and partnered with Business Engagement Leads to deliver annual value improvements for a competitive industry advantage.
- Worked with various staff members and department Leads to solve any workflow or conflict issues.
- Implemented and evaluated short- and long-range performance improvement operational goals and objectives for the department to maximize ROI.
- Developed and executed physician procurement/onboarding strategies that aligned with the specialty needs of the company including program licensing and facility electronic records training.
- Worked with physicians and staff for electronic health records training and implementation as well has protected health records HIPPA compliance.
- Provided leadership, instruction and supervision to 30 personnel with efforts resulting in a 20% decrease in staff turnover.
- Maintained accountability for over \$3 millions of medical equipment- led to zero loss in over a 12-month period.

# Quality Assurance Manager

Sep 2018 - July 2020

## **ScribeAmerica** - Sugar Land, TX

- Manage the quality of Scribe America's Hospital contracts by optimizing and ensuring best practices including activities including HIPAA training and education, Chief Scribe development, Scribe America compliance, leadership, management, communications skills, scheduling, and planning.
- Promoting client-focused and responsive services for Hospital contracts, with a strong focus on consistent scribe quality, scribe "best practice" standards, and continuing scribe education.
- Meeting with other QAMs and the Regional Manager bi-monthly to ensure stability of each location, consistent quality of all hospital scribes, and ensuring each location is using a standardized company protocol for training.
- Promoting the use of www.ScribeAmericaTraining.com to continue online education for Continuing Scribe education Credits.

#### **General Surgeon**

March 2015 - Dec 2017

# Mobile M.D./Physician Jan 2011 - April 2015

## Amar Hospital - Surgical Intensive Care Unit - Patiala, India

- Assisted on over 200 surgeries, including open cholecystectomies, appendectomies and hernia repairs.
- Assisted in the management of patients and provide back-up support to the consultant.
- To supervise the daily clinical management of all patients in conjunction with the nurse team leaders and under the guidance of Trauma Surgery Consultants attending to all post-operative patients on day of surgery and every day following.
- Ensure completion of the HOSPILOGIX ELECTRONIC HEALTH Systems.

# APPS Para-medical Services - Los Angeles, CA

- Conducted over 5,000 mobile/at-home healthcare screenings providing accurate whole health information to a variety of clients who were not able to go to local hospitals/clinics.
- Carried out M.D. Physical Exams, Assessments and recommended treatments/referrals.
- Carried out daily B.P, weight, temperature and at home Blood Draws (1,000+)
- Processed HIPPA approved patient online access to health history paperwork and results.

# **Data Analytics Projects**



- A study of a medical staffing agency covering U.S. hospitals that requires a retrospective data analysis study in order to gain insight for temporary healthcare worker placement for the upcoming Influenza season.
- Using core data analytic tools, we profile, clean and use statistical data to forecast the need for staff in locations with the most deaths, to ensure lives are saved in the future.
- This project used insight from the past in order to prepare for the future, giving hospitals the correct staff to decrease expenditures and direct sources where they are most needed.









- A study of how the world has been affected by and adjusted to the COVID-19 pandemic.
- From the increased number of deaths, to the effect the virus has had on the world's economy, we use machine learning models and data forecasting via Python to look at the past and plan for the future.
- This project showed us what we did wrong and what we need to do right to ensure innocent people do not lose their lives to such a deadly diseases.











- A fictional video films library company needs data analysis-based insight to compete with online streaming video platforms like Amazon, Netflix and Apple and setup an efficient online film library.
- Using SQL data base queries, filtering, joins, cleaning and common table expressions, we can study customer preferences, patterns & spending trends to maximize ROI goals.
- By putting the customer/client first, we gain market brand recognition, loyalty and a brand following, to stand out from the rest.









### Skills & Tools

### Data Analysis Skills

Data wrangling





Data Merging







Aggregating Data

**Grouping Data** 

Visualizations





seaborn

**Consistency Checks** 





#### **Soft Skills**

Empathy
Active Listening
Interpersonal Communication
Creative Problem-Solving
Collaboration

Team Building Easily Adaptable Organization Leadership

Long Term Planning

**Goal Orientated** 

"Get things done!" attitude

### **Languages/Tools Experience**

Spanish – Fluent written & Spoken

Hindi/Punjabi – Fluent written & Spoken

PostgreSQL – Large Data base access and manipulation, joining, insight and visualization display.

Python/Anaconda/Jupyter – read, write, complex joining, flag creations, and visualizations using Plotly, Matplotlib, Pandas, Numpy and many more.

Tableau – geographical, table based & multi-perceptive data visualizations

Visual Studio Code, Excel with macros, PowerPoint

GitHub – upload, processing, displaying of repositories